OK, so let's start back up.
Today, let's see.
We are transitioning from morphology into phonetics.
So I hope you enjoyed morphology.
It's not as if you won't ever do any morphology again,
but that's it for lessons on morphology, lectures, I guess.
Today is phonetics, which means that today we
begin making funny sounds at each other.
So everybody limber up your vocal tracks.
Let's see.
I'm trying to remember if there's anything
that I ought to announce.
You remember maybe that problem set one, which
confusingly is your second problem set, is due on Thursday.
Normally it would be due on Tuesday,
but because I am technologically challenged,
it's due on Thursday.
Speaking of being technologically challenged,
I just figured out how to get the projector to project
over there instead of in the middle
so that I won't have to write everything twice running back
and forth across the room.
So thank you.
I'm going to mention this when I go up for, you know,
my chair is trying to decide whether to give me a raise.
I'll be like, big academic achievements of the year.
Figuring out the techniques.
So if anybody misses the old days,
like you were used watching me run back and forth,
or this turns out to be too small or something like that,
let me know, and we'll go back to the old days.
So when we speak, if we're speaking an oral language,
if we're not signing, what we are typically doing
is producing a flow of air, which typically comes out
of your lungs, but not necessarily.
We'll talk about that.
And it gets obstructed in various ways in the vocal tract.
And so one standard way of talking
about different kinds of speech sounds
is to talk about where in the vocal tract things the flow
of air can get obstructed and how.
And that's what we're going to kind of do.
So first, we'll talk about where.
So one way of categorizing the various things
that your vocal tract does to the airflow
is by what's called place of articulation.
That is, where in your vocal tract
is the flow of air getting obstructed.
So for example, there are what are called bilabial sounds.
These are sounds which are made with both lips.
This picture over here on the right
is what's called a sagittal section.
That is, it's a picture of someone's head cut in half
so that you can see the stuff that's inside.
And those arrows are meant to get you
to imagine that this person is making a sound
by putting their two lips together.
So that's what you do for the sounds
that are at the beginnings of words like paint and bath
and mouth and, well, wipe, where your lips don't touch,
but they both move.
Everybody, feel free to confirm to yourselves
the privacy of your own mask that that is what you're
doing when you make these sounds.
Now, next to the sounds, so I have these words, paint, bath,
and wipe, and then next to them I
have these symbols in brackets.
And they may not look at it, but these
are extremely technical symbols.
These are symbols of the international phonetic alphabet.
So linguists have a system for writing sounds down
so that we'll all know what kind of sound we're talking about
when we're talking about sounds.
And bless you, a lot of the symbols
of the international phonetic alphabet
resemble letters of the English alphabet.
So we have started here with symbols
that should all look kind of familiar.
So the symbol for the sound at the beginning of paint
is the letter P. And so that's a symbol
of the international phonetic alphabet.
As we go along, we will be seeing weirder and weirder
symbols from the international phonetic alphabet.
So please enjoy it while it's easy.
So far so good.
There are also what are called labiodental sounds.
Labiodental sounds involve your top teeth and your lower lip.
If you think about what you're doing
at the beginning of a sound like face or vase,
what you're doing, at least if you're me,
is bringing your lower lip pretty close to your upper teeth
and obstructing the flow of air there
so that there's some turbulence.
There are, I believe, no languages in which labiodentals
are made with your bottom teeth and your upper lip.
It's a little hard to do face, face.
We'll talk about other kinds of places of articulation
that English doesn't use.
But I think that one just doesn't exist.
And again, two symbols of the IPA,
which, again, are not going to be too hard for you to learn.
Yeah, so the symbol for the sound at the beginning of face
is an F. The symbol for the sound at the beginning of vase
is a V. Here we get our first two IPA symbols that
are not letters of the English alphabet.
These are interdental sounds.
Interdental sounds are cross linguistically not hugely
common.
We have them in English.
There are various dialects of Arabic that have them.
Some of the Berber languages have them.
But they're not all that common.
These are the sounds at the beginnings of words
like thistle and this, where you're
sticking your tongue between your front teeth
and making air flow out.
English doesn't spell these differently, at least not
reliably.
So we spell both of these with a th.
That's one of the reasons the International Fanatic Alphabet
is there, so that we can unambiguously talk
about what we're talking about.
So the sound at the beginning of thistle
and the sound at the beginning of this,
they're not the same sound.
We'll talk about the difference between them shortly.
But at this point, maybe it's just clear,
they're not the same sound.
So there are two different IPA symbols for them.
The Greek letter theta is used for the sound
at the beginning of thistle.
And that second letter is an old English letter.
It's still used in Icelandic.
It's sometimes called ev, and it
stands for the sound at the beginning of this.
Then there are what are called alveolar sounds.
If you put your tongue at the top of your mouth
and kind of drag it, so put it first against your front teeth,
and then kind of drag it backwards
along the top of your mouth.
If you're like me, you've got your teeth,
and then there's this kind of flat-ish space,
and then it kind of goes up.
So from your teeth, you go back, there's a little plateau.
There's this little plateau there right behind your teeth,
this gum ridge, and then your mouth begins to go up higher.
That ridge is called the alveolar ridge.
And if you put your tongue there,
then you are all set to make sounds
like the sound at the beginning of the word teeth or duck
or nail.
And for sounds like sail and zoom,
again, you're not actually touching that position.
We'll talk more about the difference between S and T
in just a second.
But they're both alveolar sounds.
Your tongue is pointing in the general direction
of your alveolar ridge.
Everybody have that sensation?
You should all be exploring the insides of your own heads
right now.
There's a type of sound that has been called alveopalital.
It's also called post-alveolar.
I'll call it post-alveolar.
If you think first about an S, and then you
think about a shh, the shh at the beginning of shit.
If you go back and forth between them,
shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh.
You make a very soothing sound.
Yeah?
And maybe what you can feel is that your tongue
and maybe what you can feel is that your tongue
is kind of rocking back and forth.
At least that's what my tongue is doing.
For S, it's kind of pointing at the front,
at my alveolar ridge.
And then for shh, the middle of my tongue
kind of curls up a little bit, goes a little further back.
Is that the feeling people are having?
Is there going back and forth between these?
Here's another new symbol.
That's the symbol for the sound at the beginning of ship.
And another new symbol, that's the sound
in the middle of azure, the shh sound.
Both of those are post-alveolar sounds.
You'll sometimes see them called alveopalital sounds.
I'll try to remember to always call them post-alveolar.
Yep.
A little further back, there are
what are called palatal sounds.
These are even further behind the alveolar ridge,
sort of back where the roof of your mouth
gets as high as it's going to get.
And the one palatal sound that we have in English
is the y sound at the beginning of year.
And here's the first IPA symbol that is deliberately
designed to confuse you.
The IPA symbol for that sound, the y at the beginning of year,
is a j.
This is because the IPA was not invented exclusively
by speakers of English.
So it was invented also by speakers of languages
like German, in which they used this letter for this sound.
Ja, for example, the German word for yes, it's spelled ja.
OK.
The letter y is used for something else.
We'll get to it.
And then, sort of continuing our tour of the mouth.
So we're working our way backwards through the mouth.
There are what are called velar sounds.
In the velar sound, the body of your tongue
is up against what's called the velum, which
is the soft tissue at the back of your mouth
that we're going to be hearing more about in a second.
It's responsible for partitioning your mouth
from your nose, from your oral cavity.
So that's the place that your tongue is touching
when you say the sounds at the beginnings of words
like colonel and caught and gone.
And when you make the nasal sound at the end of a word
like sing, so if you think about where your tongue is,
it's up in the back there.
Does that sound right?
Yeah?
Cool.
And then, going even further down.
Further down in your throat, you've
got the vocal cords of the glottis, this space that's
down there in your throat around your larynx.
And your vocal cords, or they're sometimes
called your vocal folds.
This process that you've got back here in your throat
for closing off the air can be closed
to make what's called a glottal stop.
English doesn't make a huge amount of use of the glottal
stop, but it's what shows up at the beginnings of words
like, uh-uh, that catch that you're getting in your throat,
uh-uh, meaning no, right?
Or, uh-oh, meaning oh dear.
That catch that you're getting in your throat,
that's a glottal stop.
There are languages that are into glottal stops.
They have lots of them.
English is not.
And then, so that's what, and the way you make that
is by basically slamming your vocal folds together
to close off the flow of air.
You can also hold them kind of close together
and let the air whistle past.
That's how you make an H, right?
As in, what's my word up there?
Help, yeah?
So you're just slightly abrading the flow of air.
OK?
Now, yeah, are there questions about any of that?
So that was just a quick tour through the vocal tract.
Yeah?
Where is my cha?
Oh, we haven't gotten to cha.
Yeah, but good question.
We can think of what that is.
Cha, a cha sound at the beginning of a word like church.
Also at the end of a word like church.
Is a kind of dynamic sound, right?
I think your tongue is in motion as you are making that sound.
So it makes one sort of, it completely stops the flow there
and then it gradually peels back and allows the air to flow out.
You could think of that first thing
it's doing as, I'm on completely the wrong slide,
as being like an alveolar stop, right?
So it's like a T, right?
It's like a T. And then as it peels back,
you end up with something like a cha, like a post alveolar.
So it's a pretty complicated sound.
And we'll talk about it.
Yeah, that's a really good question.
Are there questions?
Somebody had a question?
Yeah?
What's the difference between an alveolar stop and an ending constant?
I'm sorry, say it again.
What's the difference between an alveolar stop and say an ending constant?
An ending constant?
What kind of ending constant did you get?
Oh, oh, oh, yeah, so that's a really good point.
OK, so a glottal stop, take a word like put, right?
If you say put, your tongue, at least my tongue,
touches the alveolar ridge.
It goes where I said it would.
But you're right.
You also make a glottal stop, at least the way I just said it.
Put, yeah.
You could contrast that.
If you didn't make the closure at the alveolar ridge,
it would sound like put, right?
Which is not an English word for me.
There are dialects of English in which you would say,
in which that's something you would say, right?
Put.
There are places in English where things
that we write as other kinds of sounds actually
are, in fact, glottal stops, at least in my English.
So the difference for me between can and can't,
my wife, who is Japanese, is driven crazy
by the difference between can and can't.
Because they're virtually the same, right?
It's very hard for her to figure out often,
whether I'm saying can or can't.
Because the difference between them is really mostly just,
can't is really just can plus a glottal stop.
I'm not saying can't, usually, unless I'm being very emphatic.
Yeah?
Good question.
Yes?
It's a little bit difficult for the same sound
to be heard, honestly, but with a different sound.
Yes?
Yes, there are things like that.
Do you have something in mind?
Oh, OK.
So we haven't gotten yet to R. We'll get to R, eventually.
But actually, people discovered at a certain point.
So people investigate this kind of thing in all kinds of ways.
One is the kind of thing we're all doing,
where we just sort of sit and say, what is my mouth doing?
Hm.
There's other kinds of work where people, classically,
paint the roof of your mouth with stuff that will come off.
And then you have people produce a sound,
and then you stick a camera in their mouth and take pictures
and see which parts of the paint came off.
You stick tubes down people's nose to measure airflow.
You do all kinds of horrible, invasive things.
These days, people do a lot of MRIs.
I'm going to put on the website a couple of websites
that have charts of all of the sounds
that we're going to talk about plus many more,
together with MRIs of the people's insides of people's mouths
making these sounds so that you can sort of see the anatomy that's
involved.
You won't just have to think about it.
One of the things people have discovered
as they're doing this kind of work
is that people just have different ways of producing R,
that there are just different kinds of things
you can do with your anatomy to make an R sound.
And that's probably related to the fact
that R is one of the kinds of sounds
that people classically have trouble with.
If you've been around small children, for example,
it's kind of standard for them to not quite get R, right?
And to say something that sounds more like a W
at a certain stage.
So I'm sorry, the short answer to your question is yes.
And R might be an example.
Yeah, good questions.
Any other things people want to talk about?
OK.
So I went through that.
So now I already sort of alluded to the fact
that I had these slides that had various places
of articulation on them.
But of course, each slide had multiple sounds on it.
And so the place of articulation is obviously
not the whole story.
Here's another part of the story.
It's what's called voicing.
So if you think about an S and a Z,
those are both alveolar sounds.
Your tongue is reaching toward the alveolar ridge.
But they're not the same.
What's the difference between them?
If you think about, if you go back and forth between them,
zzzz, zzzz, zzzz, zzzz, you can feel a buzzing.
And if you put your hand right here, sorry,
you put your hand right here, right here on your throat,
then when you make the zzzz sound,
you can sort of find the source of that buzzing.
It's right there in your larynx.
What's happening when you make a zzzz
is that you're holding your vocal folds
across the flow there in such a way
that they will flap in the breeze as the air goes by.
They'll vibrate.
That's like whistling with a blade of grass,
or playing a reed instrument.
You're getting something to vibrate really fast.
And that's what you're hearing.
That's that buzzing sound that you're hearing and feeling
if you put your hand right here when you're doing a zzzz.
We say that zzzz is voiced and that szzz is voiceless.
It's a distinction in voicing.
Yes?
Is the fact that it's not holding the throat
in the breeze?
Yeah, so the difference between cats and dogs?
Yeah.
So exactly, I was going to get to that later,
but yes, that's exactly it.
So what's the difference between a cat and a dog?
Well, as far as a phenologist is concerned,
the difference is that cat and dog end in sounds
that differ in voicing.
Is t voiced or voiceless?
The t at the end of cat?
Voiceless.
And the g at the end of dog is voiced.
And you're choosing s or z.
You're putting the sound that agrees in voicing
with the constant that's at the end.
That's exactly right.
Yeah?
So then, is it possible to whist the zzzz?
Yeah, so this is a really good question,
which I was hoping not to get asked quite so soon,
but no, that's good.
OK, so she just asked, what are you
doing when you're whispering?
So if you think about what you're
doing when you're whispering, first of all,
your vocal cords are not vibrating at all.
Your vocal cords are not vibrating at all at any point.
So that should mean that you're not
making the distinction between s and z, or between f and v.
Or what's my other example here?
The and the, right?
So the difference between bath and bath
is that the v is voiced and the th is voiceless.
But that doesn't seem to be true, right?
I mean, if you whisper safe and save,
safe, save, you have the feeling
that you can hear the difference between them, yeah?
I think if you were to whisper one of these,
so do a controlled experiment, go back to your dorm,
whisper to your dorm mate, safe,
and then find out what they think you said.
Maybe warn them in advance, what you're going to do.
I really, really, oh boy, the complaints.
Yes, so there's got to be something else going on, right?
Let's do this experiment again, though.
So it's easiest for you, actually, with f and v.
So let's do this thing again.
If we go back and forth between f and v,
which of them is voiced?
The v, right?
The v is voiced.
OK, now do it again, but whisper.
Does anybody feel a difference between f and v?
I mean, not here, right?
Yeah?
So I, yes?
Yeah, there might be a difference
in the aperture of your mouth, I think you're right.
And I think you're right, too, that there's
a difference in how fast the air is flowing.
For me, I actually have the opposite of your feeling.
For me, for me, there's more air when there's an f,
and less air when there's a v, I don't know.
Yeah?
It does need, but when I see v, it might look a little narrower.
Ooh.
Yeah, my jaw is moving as I do that.
And I think that is affecting what my lips are doing.
They're coming together more.
So I think what's happening, maybe,
maybe is an attempt to answer your question, is that,
so I just said, sounds can be either voiced or voiceless.
If they're voiced, what it means is that your vocal cords
are vibrating.
And I made it sound like the way you do that
is, well, you stick your vocal cords into the flow of air,
and you make them vibrate.
But I think maybe what we're learning
is that you do some other things, too,
to optimize the flow of air so that you
will get a good vibration going.
That maybe if the flow of air is too fast,
and maybe we're learning things about the aperture
of your mouth as well, there's a way of making sure
that the pressure that you're getting,
the sort of rush of air that you're getting on your vocal
cords, will make them vibrate in just the right way.
And you're manipulating all of that stuff
without thinking about it.
And you can still hear it when you whisper.
So when you whisper, you're not engaging your vocal cords,
but you're doing all the other stuff.
And that's what you're using to hear the difference.
There's experimental work on this,
is the kind of thing people try to figure out.
Yeah, really good question.
OK.
OK, so your vocal cords can either be vibrating
or they cannot be vibrating.
You have voiced sounds, and you have voiceless sounds.
So S and Z and T and D are all alveolar,
but S and T are voiceless, and Z and D are voiced.
Does that all sound right?
Is anyone upset by any of that?
Disturbed, alarmed, hungry.
Yeah, anything?
OK, good.
So back to the Polish plurals.
So we saw before we convinced ourselves,
or I convinced myself, and I tried
to take the rest of you with me, kind of as collateral damage,
that Polish has words that end in K
and words that end in G underlyingly,
but it also has a rule that changes G to K
at the ends of words.
That was Polish, right?
OK, but it's not just G. So we can see some other pairs of words.
I don't have any more minimal pairs for you,
but you can see there's the same general tendency
that if we look at singulars in Polish,
that they can end in sounds like K or P or T or S.
That's what we're seeing in these pairs.
And that when you pluralize them, some nouns that end in P
still end in P when you add the E, the suffix, like corpse,
but some change the P to a B. And the same deal
for these other ones.
So what we're learning is it isn't just
that G becomes K at the end of a word in Polish.
There's this more general thing.
What's the more general thing?
What's going on here?
What's the difference between G and K?
So they're both velar.
Yeah.
Yeah, which one is voiced?
The G. So what's happening is that the G, which was voiced,
is becoming voiceless at the ends of words in Polish.
What's happening with B and P?
Joseph?
Voice A becomes voiceless.
Yeah, the voiced B becomes the voiceless version, which is P.
Those are both bilabial sounds.
They involve both your lips.
Yes?
How is D voiced?
Sorry?
Oh, B.
B.
B. You're raising a good point.
There's a reason that I started with sounds like S and Z
and F and V, because you can go for as long as you have breath.
Whereas B, there's a limit to how long you can be.
We just said the way voicing works
is that you've got air flowing across your vocal folds
and making them vibrate.
And for a Z, you can see how that would work.
So the air just flows.
For a B, well, the air only has so far to go.
That's one reason you can't keep a B going for very long.
All that air has to get in.
It has to flow past your vocal folds
to get them to vibrate a little bit.
And then it gets to your mouth, and then it has to stop.
There are other departments that are better at this than I am,
but the air pressure in your mouth
is going to build up past a certain point.
You won't be able to keep doing that.
But you do it for as long as you can.
That's the sense of much it's voiced.
Yeah, good question.
Yeah?
OK.
So yeah, what's happening in Polish is not just G becomes K.
It's voiced sounds are becoming voiceless.
So Z becomes S, D becomes T, B becomes P, and G becomes K.
So it's sometimes called final devoicing.
And it's a cross-linguistically quite common phenomenon.
OK.
So yeah.
All right.
So we've talked about place of articulation,
and we've talked about voicing.
Now we need to talk about another dimension
for categorizing sounds, which is called
manner of articulation.
So think about S and T. They're both alveolar
and they're both voiceless.
But they're different from each other.
And the way we distinguish them is via what
we call manner of articulation.
So they're both voiceless alveolar sounds.
But T is a stop, and S is what's called a fricative.
So stops are also called plosives.
I promise never, ever to call them plosives.
I will always call them stops, because that's
what I grew up calling them.
But you will sometimes see things written in which
they're called plosives.
In homeworks, if you ever need to write about them,
feel free to call them either one.
Doesn't matter.
I like calling them stops, because they're
named after the fact that, well, they stop the flow there.
That's what they do.
That's what a stop is.
So the error is coming out of your lungs, and it gets stopped.
Fricatives, like S, are sounds in which you don't stop the flow
there, but you narrow some aperture
enough to create turbulent airflow, which you hear
as a kind of hissing sound.
So sounds like S, and sh, and f, and f.
These are all fricatives.
So for T and D, the airflow is stopped.
For S and Z, the airflow is restricted, but is not stopped.
So you kind of hold your tongue close to the alveolar ridge,
but you allow air to keep flowing through.
That's why, since the conversation we just had,
that's why an S, you can keep going
for as long as you have breath in your lungs,
whereas a T, you can't keep executing it.
So now we have these three ways of categorizing
these kinds of speech sounds.
Place and manner and voicing.
Place of articulation, manner of articulation, and voicing.
So there are a bunch of places of articulation
over there on the left.
And the sounds that we have mainly talked about
have been either stops or fricatives.
And then each of these places on the table,
there's a pair of sounds.
And I hope I managed to do this right.
Yes, it looks like I did.
In all of these pairs, you've got both a voiced
and a voiceless sound.
Which one is first?
The voiced sound.
So in all of those, there's a pair.
So you've got zh and sh, for example,
the post-alveolar fricatives.
And the zh is the voiced one.
And the sh is the voiceless one.
Yeah?
OK, good.
All right.
So now, new class of sounds.
This is a new manner of articulation.
So we've got d, which is a voiced alveolar stop,
and zh, which is a voiced alveolar fricative.
And now we need to think about n.
Well, n is voiced, and it's a stop in the sense
that you are stopping the air from flowing through your mouth.
If you think about what's happening inside your mouth
during an n, your tongue is jammed
against your alveolar ridge, just as it would be for a t.
So I love the sound of phonetics in the morning.
It's great.
So when you're doing an n, you've
stopped the flow of air in your mouth,
and so n is technically a stop.
It's called a stop because there's no air coming out
of your mouth.
But there's air coming out somewhere.
It's coming out of your nose.
And you can tell because if you hold your nose,
you will not be able to make an n.
So the reason that you can keep an n going again
for as long as you have breath is, well,
the air has some place to go.
It's going out your nose.
What's happening when you make an n
is that you are lowering the velum, which
is this doohickey in the back of your mouth
that partitions your nose from your mouth.
By lowering it, you're allowing air to flow through your nose.
So for t and d, the airflow is stopped at the alveolar ridge.
For n, the airflow is also stopped at the alveolar ridge.
It can't go through the mouth.
It's stopped right there, but it goes through your nose.
This is a nasal stop, a voiced alveolar nasal.
People often just call them nasals
because nasal fricatives are messy.
Actually, not possible, possibly.
OK?
So let me go back.
n is an alveolar nasal.
What would a bilabial nasal sound like?
Close your lips and allow the air to flow through your nose.
And a velar nasal?
Remember that velar means the place of articulation
for a k or a g.
So you make a k or a g sound, and then just
let air flow through your nose.
That's the sound at the end of a word like song, or king,
or making a velar nasal.
English doesn't allow words to begin with velar nasals,
but there are languages that do.
So Tagalog, for example, the word for now, right now,
is ngayun.
So it starts with a velar nasal.
One of the entertaining things about learning Tagalog
is learning how to make sounds that start with velar nasals.
You're an English speaker, you're not used to it.
Yeah?
OK, so there's the table again.
So we've got stops and fricatives and nasals.
Nasal stops.
Things can be voiced or voiceless.
And we've got all those places of articulation
over there on the left.
Are there questions about any of this?
Is anybody looking at this and saying, whoa,
this table has grown out of my ability to keep a word?
Yeah?
Yeah.
What English doesn't allow?
English doesn't allow words to begin with velar nasals.
We don't have any words that start with the sound
that's at the end of words like song.
We don't have words like ngayun.
English doesn't have words like that.
There are plenty of languages that do.
Tagalog is one.
Cantonese is one.
There are a bunch of others.
But English doesn't have that.
Yes?
I noticed there's not a j in practice or a y.
It's called paladol.
Oh, yeah.
Actually, I don't actually know where this j would go.
Yeah.
So we haven't yet gotten to the kind of sound
that that j, the sound at the beginning of the year.
You're absolutely right.
There's a gap there.
And I've put the paladol line there partly
to get you to ask exactly that kind of question.
So one of the points of this table,
it's kind of like when the periodic table was first
invented, I guess.
So we have this system for categorizing sounds.
And now we get to look at it and say, well, wait, why
isn't there anything there or there?
And what would it be like if it were there?
We'll do a little bit of that in a second.
But yeah, you're right.
So we haven't yet talked about the kind of sound
that the IPA symbol j, the sound we usually
write with y in English, the sound at the beginning of the year,
we haven't put that on the table yet.
You're right.
It's not a stop.
It's also not a fricative because you're not making
any turbulence in the airflow.
And it's not nasal.
So it's another kind of thing.
We'll get to it.
Good question.
Other questions?
This?
OK.
All right.
So yeah, OK.
So this way of classifying the sounds
leads us to wonder about gaps.
This is, yes, thanks.
Norvin, yeah, you set that up nicely.
So let's think about some of these gaps.
So English, for example, has bilabial stops, P and B.
And it has a bilabial nasal and M. But it
doesn't have a bilabial fricative.
What would a bilabial fricative sound like?
It would sound kind of like blowing out a candle.
Open your lips just enough to let some air come out and then
blow.
That's a bilabial trill.
We will get to that.
Either that or you were just having fun, I'm not sure.
There are languages that have that.
So but a bilabial fricative, English
doesn't have a bilabial fricative.
But there are languages that do.
Japanese does, for example.
So in Japanese, the sound that when
people are writing Japanese in the Roman alphabet,
when they write an F, like when they
write the name of this mountain, they'll write it with an F.
But in Japanese, that's not an F.
It's a bilabial fricative.
It's Fuji, Fuji.
If you learn Japanese, you must learn to pronounce
the F bilabially rather than labiodentally.
So in English, we have a labiodental F
with our lower lip against our teeth.
In Japanese, F, your teeth are not involved.
It is only your lips.
What would a bilabial fricative sound like?
Is this a voice or a voiceless bilabial fricative?
Voiceless.
What would it sound like if it were voiced?
Vrr.
And that exists, too.
There are dialects of Spanish, for example,
that have that between vowels.
If you have the letter B between vowels in words like aruela,
that B has that sound, a voiced bilabial fricative.
Moving across the chart, I've got a nasal stop there.
Is that nasal voiced or voiceless?
Voiced.
What would it sound like if it were voiceless?
I should step back.
English doesn't have that.
But there are languages out there that do.
Languages like Hmong, for example,
which is a minority language spoken in,
actually it's quite a large minority language spoken
in Vietnam.
Hmong has that kind of sound.
Tibetan has that kind of sound, too.
OK.
Let's skip palatal and do velar.
We've got velar stops in English, K and G, and G.
And we've got velar nasals.
What would a velar fricative sound like?
Yes.
She's alerting me that she's not just hissing at me.
She's making a velar fricative.
Yes.
Is that a voiced or a voiceless velar fricative?
Voiceless, yeah.
English doesn't have that.
But there are languages that do.
Languages like German say that's one of the sounds
that they write with the letters C and H. At the end of composers
names like Bach, Johann Sebastian Bach.
His name ends with a velar fricative.
Russian has this sound.
Shows up in the names of authors like Chekhov.
Sound.
What would a velar fricative sound like if it were voiced?
And English doesn't have that either.
But their languages that do, again,
they're dialects of Spanish, where
if you have a G between vowels, it'll
get this kind of sound in words like agua.
So we've talked about various kinds of nasals.
Nasal stops.
So an M is a bilabial nasal, right?
Where you close the flow there at your lips
and allow the air to flow through your nasal cavity
by lowering your velums.
You get an N. Or you can stop the flow there in other places.
You can have an alveolar nasal, right?
N, you can have a velar nasal.
What would a glottal nasal sound like?
Trick question, you would need surgery.
So the way nasal stops work is you're
stopping the flow of air somewhere in your vocal tract,
but you're allowing the air to flow through your nasal cavity.
That's what a nasal stop is.
Here, let's get back to one of these sedgital sections.
So that N there, right?
What you're doing is you're stopping the flow of air
there at the alveolar ridge, right?
But you're lowering the velum to let the air flow through.
Or an M, you'd be closing the flow of air at your lips
and lowering your velum to let the air flow through.
Or a velar nasal, a N, like at the end of King.
You're making a closure at the velum,
but you're also lowering the velum and letting
the air flow through.
A glottal nasal, you'd have to stop the flow of air down
there at the vocal folds and let the air go through your velum.
But if you're stopping it down there,
it can't be going through your velum.
So you would need, again, as I say,
probably there are unethical surgeons who would modify you
so that you could make glottal nasals.
You need extra ways to get air to flow through your nasal cavity.
I'm not recommending this, by the way.
All right.
Cool.
So those are some of the gaps.
Oh, and I flagged a gap that I didn't talk about.
Sorry, a couple of gaps.
So English has interdental fricatives, th and the.
And as I said, those are cross-linguistically kind
of rare, which is why if you're trying
to do an accent from various kinds of places,
for example, in Europe, one of the things you do
is replace your TH sounds with other kinds of sounds.
So if you're doing a French accent,
you replace your TH sounds with Zs.
Or if you're doing a German accent,
you replace your TH sounds with Ts.
English has interdental fricatives,
and it has alveolar stops, T and D. There are languages out there
that have what are called dental stops.
So a dental stop, so the alveolar stop, again,
involves your tongue touching the alveolar ridge
and stopping the flow there, there.
For a dental stop, your tongue is touching your teeth.
So you're not saying atah.
You're saying atah, atah, atah.
English does not have those, but there are languages out there
that do.
If you're studying another language,
this is a kind of thing to think about,
because sometimes your teacher will not
be thinking about this.
But you should be asking yourself,
is this sound that sounds sort of like a T?
Is it an alveolar T or is it a dental T?
Part of your job, if you're learning
ta-da-log, for example, is to learn
to make dental Ts instead of alveolar Ts,
because that's what they've got.
Yeah?
If you're thinking about, like, with your teeth,
what say someone doesn't have teeth?
Yes, yeah?
How about that?
Well.
Would it be like a gesture?
I think, I believe that is what people do, yeah.
So you make a closure.
We can talk about interdental fricatives, right?
So somebody who doesn't have teeth and wants to do a th,
what do they do?
I think their job is to create turbulent airflow
with their tongue between where their teeth would
be if they only had teeth, right?
And I think there's something similar going on
with dental stops.
But this is exactly the kind of thing
that experimental phoneticists do,
is to try to figure out one of the things that,
they do many things, some of them kind of creepy,
to try to figure out what's going on in your vocal tract
exactly as you do this stuff.
There's all this work on what people
do to compensate for various kinds of obstructions
in the vocal tract.
So you have people bite on a block.
And you put something solid in their mouth.
And then you're like, OK, so now what
will you do with your tongue to make the sounds?
As best you can.
All kinds of weird stuff people do.
Cool stuff.
Yeah?
OK.
Where was I with all that?
OK, yeah.
So yeah, that's another set of IPA symbols.
These are your first IPA diacritics,
I guess those little square doohickeys under the t
and the d there.
Those indicate that that particular t and d, those
are dental.
There are even languages out there
that have both dental t's and alveolar t's.
So the Dravidian languages of India
are famous for having those.
And a lot of the Aboriginal languages of Australia
are really rich in places of articulation.
So has Dinka come to think of it, this Nialotic language
that I mentioned briefly that has tone as a way of marking
case.
These are all languages that have lots and lots
of places of articulation, including both dental and alveolar.
But that often don't make the languages of Australia,
at least, often don't make voicing distinctions.
So they have stops, but they don't
distinguish voiced from voiceless.
So they have places of articulation and lots of them.
And nasals in all those places as well,
but no distinction between voiced and voiceless.
Yeah?
OK, any other questions about this chart
before we zoom past it?
Like I say, I'm going to, on the website,
there will be a link to charts that
will look, hopefully, sort of like this,
more official charts by the IPA, which will have sound files
so that you can listen to trained phenologists making
the sounds.
And also, at least one website, which I hope is still up,
has MRIs so that you can watch the inside of a person's
vocal tract as they make the sound.
OK.
Now, we have been talking about parts of the vocal tract
that English uses.
Sometimes it doesn't use them for the same things
that their languages do.
So we have teeth.
We use our teeth for intradentals,
but we don't make dental stops.
But there are places in the vocal tract
that English just does not use, and yet, if other languages do.
Here are a couple.
There are what are called retroflex sounds.
These are sounds in which the tip of your tongue
is on your palate.
So instead of a t, you're making a t, a ta, a ta.
So your tongue is curled back a little bit further
than it would be for a t, and it's making a closure
if you're making a stop right there.
So you can make stops there, a ta, or a da.
You can make fricatives there, like a sha, or a ja.
And you can make nasals there, like a na, a na.
Retroflex sounds are very popular in India and Australia
and Indonesia.
They're all a good place.
Yeah?
Yeah.
In the B, there's a retroflex lateral to it.
You're right.
Out of da.
Yeah?
Mm-hmm.
Well, we'll get to laterals.
But yes, yes, there is.
Yeah?
OK, there's retroflexes.
Uvulars.
Uvulars are kind of like k, except more so.
So for a k, your back of your tongue
is hitting the back of your mouth.
It's touching your velum.
That's a k sound, akka.
For a uvular, your tongue goes further back,
and it gets at or near your uvula,
which is the little doohickey that
hangs down there at the back.
That's your uvula.
So this is a sound like akka, akka, akka, or aga,
or agha, or agha, or agha.
These are all uvular sounds.
We do not have these in English, at least
when we're feeling well.
But there are languages out there that do.
You're working on a problem set that
involves the language inupiaq.
And that letter k is a symbol for a uvular stop.
Inupiaq has a uvular stop.
It has one at the end of the name.
The inu at the beginning means people,
and piaq is a suffix meaning something
like real, or normal, or regular.
So the inupiaq are the normal people.
The rest of us are abnormal.
So yeah, uvulars, reasonably popular.
They're all over, let's see, they're
all over the indigenous languages of the Americas.
They have them in Arabic.
They're not exactly rare, but English does not have them.
The uvular voiced fricative, so the voiceless fricative,
the ch, ch, is found.
But not usually common in Europe, the r, r,
is one of the voiced uvular fricative,
is one of the ways to pronounce an r in languages
like French and German.
So if you're pronouncing the French word for red,
one of the ways to do it is with this fricative to say,
r, r, that r sound is a voiced uvular fricative.
There are other ways you can also do a uvular trill,
where you get your uvula to flap in the breeze.
But not everybody does that.
Yep, questions about that?
Makes sense?
OK.
And then there are also pharyngeals.
Pharyngeals involve constriction near the pharyngeal wall.
Arabic has these.
The Berber languages have these.
These are like, ah, ha, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah.
So you're getting the back of your tongue
to get against the back of your vocal tract.
Does anybody here speak Arabic?
OK.
So if you know anyone who speaks Arabic,
get them to speak to you for a while,
and you'll get to hear them saying this.
As I say, there will be sound files
where you'll get to hear people making these.
So English doesn't have these, but they're languages that do.
There are pharyngeal fricatives.
Yeah, those are both pharyngeal fricatives.
OK, so slightly larger chart with more symbols on it,
including some of the ones we've talked about.
Pharyngeal tubulars, rectiflexes.
And for some reason, the dental stops are still red.
I don't know why to fix that.
Yep, there's a chart.
OK.
OK, now, people keep asking me about sounds
that I've been carefully avoiding,
so let's talk about them.
There are what are called approximants.
Approximants are not stops, and they're not fricatives,
and they're not nasals.
They involve your articulators kind of vaguely gesturing
towards each other in some part of your vocal tract.
Not enough to make, definitely not making contact,
and not enough to cause any turbulence in the air flow.
So if you think about a W, let's say,
in the middle of a word like away,
that's not a stop, and it's not a fricative,
and it's not nasal.
It's bilabial, you can feel your lips engaging
as you make the W in the middle of away.
It's a bilabial sound, but it's not a bilabial stop,
or a fricative, it is a bilabial approximate.
So similarly for the Y sound at the beginning of year,
or yard, and the L and the R at the beginning and end
of, I don't know, layer, or rail, those are all approximants.
They are sometimes divided into glides and liquids,
and I'm hoping that nobody will ask me
how you know whether something is a glide or a liquid.
Are you about to ask me how you know whether something
is a glide or a liquid?
Go ahead, is that what you're?
Yes, OK, all right, fine.
So a glide, I mean, sometimes it's as though a glide
is an approximate that if you were to hold it longer,
it would be a vowel.
So a W, if you just freeze yourself in W space,
you're making an OO, right?
A W is like an OO sped up.
We're going to talk about vowels later,
but if you think about what an OO is,
it's a held version of a W. And similarly, a Y sound,
yeah, is a sped up version of an E,
as opposed to an R or an L, which are just something else.
Because I have not given you a good way of distinguishing
glides from liquids, you can trust me
that I will never ask you to distinguish them in a way that
will make a difference for grades or anything like that.
You will never see me saying, no, you're wrong,
that's not a glide, it's a liquid.
I mean, I may say that, but there won't be minus 5 next to it.
Yeah?
I mean, if the W and the Y sound are both just short and
vowel sounds, why is it necessary to have these
as separate symbols, just like the CH having two letters?
That's a really good question.
So why don't we just use the letter OO for the bilabial
glide for the W?
And let me see if I can come up with a good answer to that.
There are, eventually, we're going to get to it.
So far, all we're doing is talking about sounds individually.
And eventually, we're going to start talking about sequences
of sounds.
And we're going to want to be able to talk about restrictions
on the ways in which sounds get to interact with each other.
And so it's going to be useful at that point
to be able to distinguish, for example, consonants
from vowels.
And once we do that, and you should
feel free to call me on this if it doesn't come up later,
I'll try to make sure it does, it'll
turn out to be useful to be able to think
of the consonant version of the sound, the W,
and also the vowel version of the sound, the OO.
But you're right, that there are plenty of sound changes
where you see them converting back and forth between each other.
That's the kind of thing that happens.
So yeah, but that's the prima facie reason
for distinguishing them, because there
are rules for the distribution of sounds
for which it's useful to have that distinction.
It's like anything else, I guess.
We make that distinction as long as it turns out
to be useful for explaining stuff.
Good question.
All right.
OK, so those are quite some liquids.
OK, and then, this was Raquel who
was asking about this before, sounds like ch and j.
I think I said you could think of ch as like a stop, a T,
followed by a fricative, ch, or j,
the j at the beginning and end of a word like judge,
as being a stop, a D sound, followed by a fricative, a j.
There's a little bit of a debate about whether what I just
said is the right way to think about this or not.
I think the standard way to think about it
is not exactly that.
What people do is say, yeah, there's this package deal,
an affricate.
So there's a name for this kind of thing.
An affricate is this kind of sequence,
something like a stop, followed by a fricative.
And the arguments about whether or not
to make this move, about whether to say, no, that's
a single sound with a complex motion,
as opposed to saying, no, there's two sounds
next to each other, has to do with the kinds of considerations
I was just talking about.
When you're trying to figure out what's the best theory of,
for example, what sequences of sounds
are allowed in a syllable in a given language,
sometimes it's useful to be able to say,
this is a language that doesn't ever, ever allow,
say, a syllable to end with a stop followed by a fricative.
Oh, but it's OK for it to end with ch, you know.
So we'll just treat that as a single package.
We won't treat it as a stop followed by a fricative.
That's the kind of move people make, yeah.
So terminology, OK?
All right.
So I've made the table whiter.
There are glides, like woof and yeh.
There are some other glides there,
which I can try to read to you.
What would a labiodental glide sound like?
What's a labiodental fricative?
A voiced labiodental fricative.
V, right?
Like a V sound.
So can you try to make a labiodental glide,
maybe between vowels?
It's going to be something like, a la, a la, a la.
English doesn't have those.
I believe Hindi does.
So there are languages out there that have labiodental glides.
Similarly, there are velar glides, a la, a la, a la,
where your tongue is just kind of vaguely gesturing
in the direction of your velum.
I kind of like the IPA symbol for the velar glide.
It looks like something out of Tolkien.
Yep.
OK.
All right.
So we've done consonants.
Had not done all the consonants.
So what I'm going to do is show you some vowels.
And then we'll circle back and look
at some particularly exotic consonants, probably next time,
probably not today.
I want to start talking about vowels.
So let's go through the vowels systematically.
Compare the vowel in the middle of bead
and the vowel in the middle of bad.
And here, let me just warn you that the IPA becomes
particularly forbidding when we get to vowels in English.
And it's not the fault of the IPA.
It's the fact that English has a very large number of vowels
and not a very good system for writing them.
This is one of the things that makes English spelling so
difficult that we can actually have competitions where you
watch people spell, this kind of thing that in many languages
would be impossible.
If you tried to do that in Finnish,
the spelling bead would just never end,
because every word is pronounced exactly the way it's spelled.
We don't do that in English.
So here are two vowels, and those are their IPA symbols,
the vowel in bead and the vowel in bad.
And now, if you, so everybody joined me in sort of transitioning
from one of those vowels to the other, go yeah, yeah, yeah.
OK.
You guys sound good.
What are you doing?
I mean, you're doing what I asked you to,
but what's happening in your mouth?
Yes?
The second vowel is more open.
Yeah, the second vowel is more open.
You're opening your mouth a little bit more.
What are you doing with your tongue?
Lowering from the top to the bottom.
Yeah, it's lowering.
It's going from the top to the bottom.
Yeah, I think you guys are both right.
If your tongue is sort of tensed and it's up there
at the top of your mouth, then for ah, your tongue drops.
In fact, it drops so far that it drags your jaw down with it.
Maybe there's a more reasonable way to say that.
You lower your jaw so that your tongue can
go even further down.
So one way of classifying vowels is in terms of height.
So we talk about the high vowel like heat
and the low vowel like hat.
And there are vowels in between, like the vowel in hate.
That vowel is called mid.
So we have high vowels, and we have mid vowels,
and then we have low vowels.
Yeah?
OK, now let's do another comparison.
Think about the vowel in he and the vowel in who.
So everybody go ee, ee, ee, ee, ee.
What's going on in your vocal tract as you do that?
What's the difference between e and ooh?
Your lips, your lips are definitely involved, yes.
So for ooh, for further twist, right?
Your lips are rounded for the ooh.
That's absolutely right, yeah?
And then for heat, they're not.
Yeah?
In fact, that's why when you take photographs of people,
you have them say something with an e-vel and like cheese,
just to get them to not round their lips.
But you're doing something with your tongue, too,
as you go from ee to ooh, ee, ooh.
What are you doing with your tongue?
Yes?
Move it forward and the bottom to the floor.
Wow, so let's start with ee, where is your tongue?
I mean, it's in your mouth, but where is it pointing?
It's kind of high, right?
Ee.
And then for ooh, where does it go?
It moves, right?
So you aren't just rounding your lips
and leaving your tongue where it was, yes?
I notice for ee, my tongue has to be in my molars.
Yeah?
That's, yeah, I see what you mean, yeah?
I don't know about you guys, for me, for ee, yeah.
Yeah, for me, for ee, it's at the front and it's high.
And then for ooh, my tongue kind of curls backward
and it avoids my molars, you're absolutely right.
And it curls backwards, so it's hiding back
in the back of my mouth.
I think that's the kind of thing you were saying just now.
Yeah, is that the experience people were having?
Everybody do some more ee, ooh, ee, ooh, feel your tongue
moving back and forth.
Ignore your lips, right?
And think about your tongue, yeah?
Yeah?
OK, so we have high, mid, and low vells,
but we also have front and back vells.
So the back vells are vells like the vell in hoo
and the vell in ho, and the vell in hot, ah.
So ooh, and oh, and ah, those are all back vells.
Your tongue is sort of pulling back toward the back of your mouth.
Yeah?
And then this is the other point that you guys made.
Some of these vells are rounded.
So in English, the back non-low vells, the back high
and the back mid vells, are rounded in hoo and ho.
Your lips have to round to make those vells.
But for hot, your lips don't round.
Yeah?
And a bunch more symbols, some of them aren't so bad.
You know, the letter u for ooh, that's pretty good.
And the letter o for ooh, yeah?
And then we have that ash symbol there,
which is from Old English, for ah in had, and then e and a
and ah, go back with those.
Yeah?
We have sort of standard issue European values
for some of those symbols.
OK?
Now, in this chart, I've only got six vells.
You may have been taught, how many vells
were you taught English had if you went to school in English?
Yeah?
Five.
It's supposed to have five, right?
It does not have five.
It has like 14.
And you know, why are we taught that it only has five?
Why do we only have five letters for vells?
Who gave us this alphabet?
The Romans, right?
Yeah?
And in Latin, there in fact are five vells, which
can be either long or short.
So this is a perfect alphabet for Latin.
Yeah?
But then we got hold of it.
And so we've ended up with 12, 14 vells, different dialects
of English or different.
And we have five letters to spell them with.
And this is why we have spelling Bs.
Yeah?
One of the reasons.
OK, so I've written six of our five vells here on this chart.
And then, but we have more.
So think about O and O, right?
In Houd and Hood, or E and E, and Heed and Hid, or A and E,
and Raid and Red, or O and A, like in coat and caught.
There are various ways of talking about this distinction.
But one way is like this.
We say that there's a distinction between what
are called tense vells and what are called lax vells.
So O is a high back rounded tense vowel.
And if you go back and forth between O and O,
O, O, O, the idea is basically what you're doing is relaxing.
So your tongue is not quite as rigidly high and back
as it would be for an O when it makes an O.
And your lips are probably not quite as
tensely rounded either.
Your whole body relaxes.
Same deal with all these other pairs.
It's a fact about English lax vowels
that there's a restriction on their distribution.
English monosyllables don't end in lax vells that
are either front or high.
So we have words like flea and flu and flay.
Those are all words in English.
Flay means to remove the skin from.
But we don't have those three words at the end there.
I've given them stars to remind us
that those are not words that we could have in English.
Anybody want to attempt to pronounce them?
Yeah?
Wait, which one was it?
Oh, sorry.
You were going to ask a question.
Go ahead.
What about schwa?
We haven't gotten to schwa.
Yeah, they're more vowels.
So those last three, if they were English words,
they would be flea, flu, and flea.
Well, we don't have words like that.
English doesn't have words that end in e or o or e,
with the possible exception of meh.
So if we don't count that as a word,
then English doesn't have monosyllables
that end in these vowels.
And then you wanted to know about schwa.
Those are sometimes called central vowels.
So the first vowel in machine is a schwa.
It's not high or back.
It's not front.
It's not high or low.
It's kind of mid and central.
And then dove is pretty similar to schwa
and is sometimes represented with that wedge shape there.
In fact, it's called a wedge.
Not all speakers of English distinguish schwa from wedge.
I do.
So for me, the vowels in above are two different vowels above.
But there are speakers of English
for whom they're the same.
Similarly, I'll go back to an earlier slide.
Not every dialect of English has all of these vowels
or has them all in the same places.
So I speak a dialect of English in which
cot and cot have different vowels in them.
Does anybody pronounce those words the same?
Yeah.
I pronounce them the same, but I have a question.
Yes.
You said that they can't, like, English
also can't end in lax vowels.
What about, like, law?
OK, they're the ending.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So what did I say?
They can't end in lax vowels that are either front or high.
So yeah, you're absolutely right.
There are ones ending in awe, like, law.
Yeah, absolutely.
Or flaw.
There are people who pronounce cot and cot the same.
For me, those are two different vowels.
Yeah, can you pronounce them for us?
Cot and cot.
OK, cool.
Did you say them in the same order or a different order?
It didn't matter.
It doesn't matter.
OK, good.
I pronounce those three words, Mary, Mary, and Mary.
I pronounce them the same.
There are dialects of English that
have different pronunciations for some of them.
Does anybody pronounce these words differently?
Yeah.
Mary, Mary, and Mary.
Mary, yeah.
So there are people for whom the vowel in the last one
is more of an ash.
It's like a Mary.
I associate that with, like, New Jersey.
You're from New Jersey.
Yeah, yes.
I'll pay you later.
OK, yeah.
So OK, we've now sort of rocketed through a bunch
of consonants and the vowels.
We're just about out of time.
Let me just give this to you as an exercise,
and then we'll stop.
Anybody want to try to pronounce the first of those?
She sells seashells.
Yeah.
Tell you what, we'll do this exercise next time.
So next time, we'll do this as the first slide.
And I'll leave it on the slides.
You can work on it at home.
And do some fooling with it and try
to get to where you can read it.
As we go along, I'm going to be asking you to read things
in IPA, so I'll start putting IPA on the slides more and more.
So start trying to familiarize yourself with it
and get to where you're familiar with, at least,
the symbols for sounds that we use in English.
Do you want me to read the rest of them?
I'll do some more IPA.
OK, so what's the second one?
Sue says he's a bad egg.
Yeah, you guys are good fast learners.
And what's the third one?
Excellent.
And what's the last one?
Top chopstick shops.
Yeah, top chopstick shops, stock top chopsticks.
Got that from a book of tongue twisters.
OK, good.
So let's leave it there.
And we'll come back to this next time.